<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The creation of the Prince· A sermon preached in the Colledge of VVestminster, on Trinity Sunday, the day before the creation of the most illustrious Prince of Wales. By Daniell Price, chapleine in ordinary, and then in attendance on the Prince.</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115201</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850420</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850420</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15622</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10044)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15622)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 970:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The creation of the Prince· A sermon preached in the Colledge of VVestminster, on Trinity Sunday, the day before the creation of the most illustrious Prince of Wales. By Daniell Price, chapleine in ordinary, and then in attendance on the Prince.</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld, for Roger Iackson, dwelling neere Fleete Conduict,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15622:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15622:1"/>
            <p>THE CREATION OF THE PRINCE. A Sermon Preached in the Colledge <hi>of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſtminster, on Trinity Sunday,</hi> the day before the Creation of the moſt <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> PRINCE <hi>of Wales.</hi> By DANIELL PRICE, Chapleine in Ordinary, and <hi>then in attendance on the PRINCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>G. Eld,</hi> for Roger Iackſon, dwelling neere Fleete Conduict. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15622:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15622:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable Lord, <hi>worthy the confluence of all honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> happineſſe, ROBERT Earle of Salisbury, <hi>Lord high Treaſurer of England, one of the Oracles</hi> of his Maieſties moſt Honourable Priuie Counſaile, Knight of the treſ-noble order of the Garter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST HONOVRABLE,</hi> moſt Wiſe, moſt Worthy Lord, it is the ſecond time I preſent a <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> of my moſt humble obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance to your honour: The <hi>beames</hi> of that <hi>ſplendor</hi> of <hi>goodneſſe</hi> in you, haue ſhined vpon many ſonnes of thoſe two Siſters, the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,</hi> among whom I doe moſt ioyfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my happineſſe, in obteyning an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble promiſe, by the mediation of <hi>My royall Maiſter,</hi> the illustrious <hi>PRINCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Widowe</hi> in the <hi>Goſpell</hi> offered to the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, a litle Money; the <hi>Woman</hi> a little Oyle, <hi>to her Sauiour:</hi> Another in the Story, a little water to
<pb facs="tcp:15622:3"/>his <hi>Soueraigne:</hi> my little I offer to your honour, is much leſſe then theirs: If this ſhall adde any life to my <hi>ſuite,</hi> and procure any more fauour from your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, I ſhall acknowledge how you worthily imitate <hi>God</hi> him-ſelfe, who rewardeth <hi>an houres worke with a dayes wages:</hi> which <hi>God</hi> as hee hath already endowed you with the heart of <hi>Prudence,</hi> ſo I hope he will euer-direct your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> with his hand of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence,</hi> that you may bee <hi>famous</hi> to poſterity, <hi>grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> to This Kingdome, and <hi>glorious</hi> in His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: this I wiſh, this I pray for, thus I rest.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours in all dutifull obſeruance DANIELL PRICE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15622:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached in the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſtminſter, on Trinity</hi> Sunday, the day before the Creation of <hi>the illuſtrious and gratious Prince</hi> HENRY Prince of Wales.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 51.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Create in mee a new heart.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Reuerend, Right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Worſhipfull, and Well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued: They that haue wayed ſinnes in the ballance of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, haue found ſome to be more heauy then others, by many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, either in the Cauſality,<note place="margin">Albertus in Compend. Theolog.</note> (as the Schooles ſpeake) as that ſinne of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> or in the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> or in the deformity, as the ſinne of <hi>Iudas,</hi> or in the difficulty of Pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as the ſinne of <hi>Iulian:</hi> Theſe be ſinnes of the higheſt eleuation, towring, and mounting vp to call for perpetuall deſolation, and branded with
<pb facs="tcp:15622:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>the blackeſt character that euer any ſinnes were.</p>
            <p>For other ſinnes the auncient haue compared them to ſundry beaſts, to ſhew the beaſtlineſſe thereof, <hi>Enuie</hi> to a Dogge, <hi>Anger</hi> to a Woolfe, <hi>Sloth</hi> to an Aſſe, <hi>Auarice</hi> to a Hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hogge, <hi>Gluttony</hi> to a Beare, <hi>Luxurie</hi> to a Boare: Some others haue deſcribed them by ſome diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to manifeſt the fulſomneſſe and loathſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, <hi>Pride</hi> by an inflammation, <hi>Luxurie</hi> by a Feauer, <hi>Enuye</hi> by a Leproſie, <hi>Anger</hi> by a Phrenſie, <hi>Sloth</hi> by a Lethargie, <hi>Auarice</hi> by a Dropſie, <hi>Superſtition</hi> by the Plague, and theſe bee common, O too common euer ſince the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> receiued the tainture of bloud from the firſt offence of their firſt father!</p>
            <p>But what commerce haue the Saints with ſinnes? there is no felowſhip betweene righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and vnrighteouſneſſe, no communion betweene light and darkneſſe;<note place="margin">Gen. 25.22. 1. Sam. 5 4. Math. 21.13. Reu. 12.7. 1. Ioh. 3.9.</note> and if one wombe cannot containe <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> one houſe the <hi>Arke</hi> &amp; <hi>Dagon,</hi> one Temple <hi>prayer</hi> &amp; <hi>merchandiſe,</hi> one heauen <hi>Michael</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> how ſhall one ſoule retaine polution and ſanctification? Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> teſtifying, that he that is borne of God doth not ſinne, neither can he ſinne, becauſe hee is borne of God:<note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> but <hi>Dauid</hi> hath confeſſed though a Saint, a King, <hi>qui habuit ſanctitatem, non ſolum vnctionis ſed functionis,</hi> that by his owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he found it, that ſeauen times a day doth the righteous fall.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 46.</note> And herevpon Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile
<pb facs="tcp:15622:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe two places, asketh the queſtion, <hi>Si iuſtus quomodo cadit, ſi cadit quo modo iuſtus,</hi> and anſwereth himſelfe, that he falleth by ſinne, riſeth by grace, falleth by his fault, riſeth by his faith, or as another, <hi>homo cadit non iuſtus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanchius.</note> as a man hee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth, but as a Chriſtian man hee reconcileth himſelfe to God: and being borne of God, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not: nay as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh, he not onely doth not ſinne, but he cannot ſinne, that is,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.9.</note> deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, without remorſe they cannot ſinne, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly without feare they doe not ſinne, neither do, nor can, ſinne deſperately as <hi>Cain</hi> did, preſumptuouſly as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did; malitiouſly as <hi>Iudas</hi> did; blaſphemouſly as <hi>Iulian</hi> did, for the ſeede of God remaineth in them.</p>
            <p>Howſoeuer therefore the ſlips and ſlidings of the beſt ſeruants of God be regiſtred, that he that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth may take heed leaſt he fall, yet no one of them hath falne finally, totally: And howſoeuer, this ſweete ſinger of Iſraell (whoſe heauenly <hi>Antheme</hi> I haue choſe for this ſolemne celebrity) though his foote had almoſt ſlipt, nay though hee had fallen, and deſcended downe, downe, downe into the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of death, into the ſnares of death, into the Chambers of death, yet behold his ſunne-riſing as Orient as euer it was, he is againe created to walke in righteouſneſſe and holineſſe before God all the dayes of his life. The word CREATED, will be the ſumme of my ſucceeding diſcourſe: firſt thereby to remember thoſe many that haue this day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb facs="tcp:15622:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>holy order heere, from that honourable Prelate,<note place="margin">Lord Biſhop of Lintolne.</note> and moſt reuerend Father, who moſt carefully aduiſed them of the dignity and duty of that function, and who are now created anew, and are to forſake all the world, nay their owne ſelues, as the Diſciples did, &amp; in the prime of the Church thoſe <hi>Primitiues</hi> that would be no <hi>Poſſeſsiues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lorinus in <hi>2.</hi> Act. Apoſt.</note> ſome left all they had, others ſold all, others gaue all; ſo theſe ſhould ſo much neglect all things for Chriſtes ſake, as that they were at the firſt created to the image of the earthly man, earthly, ſo now they ſhould be created to the image of the Lord from heauen, heauenly.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, my choice of this Text was chiefly to ſolemnize this great Feaſt of the CREATION and inueſtiture of my moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord and Maiſter the Prince, to adde ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity to which Feaſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 148.</note> were I as able as willing, I would take the courſe that <hi>Dauid</hi> in 140. Pſalme, to call from the heauens, the Angels, and armies thereof, Sunne, Moone, Starres, heauens of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and the waters that be aboue the heauens, I would deſcend from the orbes and arches, and ſummon the ayre, fire, ſnow, vapors, and winds. I would enter into the Ocean,<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> and raiſe the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, and all deepes, fiſhes of the ſeas, and all that paſſeth through the pathes of the ſeas. I would warne a Conuocation of all the world, and muſter together mountains, and all hilles, fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full trees, and all Cedars, beaſtes and all cattell,
<pb facs="tcp:15622:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>creeping thinges and feathered fowles, Kings of the earth, and all people, Princes and all Iudges of the world, young men and maidens, old men and children to praiſe the name of the Lord: for if euer, now we may ſay, Bleſſed be the eyes, that ſee the things that we ſee, ſo royall, learned, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a King, ſo noble, worthy &amp; gracious a Prince, the kingly father ſo happy, ſo excellent, the prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sonne ſo rarely vertuous, ſo obedient, though I will not ſay as thoſe heathen did of the Apoſtles, gods haue deſcended to vs in the likeneſſe of men, yet I will with the heathen Hiſtorian confeſſe,<note place="margin">Xenophon.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Prince is an Image of God, which ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is the moſt glorious chaplet, coronet, frontlet, tablet, bracelet of a Chriſtian Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Temp.</note>At the Feaſt of the Natiuity wee are taught to bee borne againe: at the Feaſt of Eaſter to riſe againe, at the Feaſt of Whitſontide to pray for the ſpirit, at this Feaſt of Trinitie to receiue the ſpirit, and by this great and ſolemne long wiſhed-for Feaſt of this CREATION, wee are taught to pray for the creating of new hearts, good ſoules, religious ſpirits, honeſt conſciences. And howſoeuer the head of my Text ſerueth only for the Prince, the CREATION, yet the body of my Text ſerueth for all people, it is the renouation of the mind <hi>[Create in me a new heart]</hi> I haue prouided this meſſenger to ſend vp to heauen for new ſouls; an ambaſſadour quicke of ſpeed, faithfull for truſt, happy for ſucceſſe, whom neither the tediouſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:15622:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the time, nor difficulty of the paſſage can hinder, but as a chariot of fire will preſently be lifted vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of the Almighty to ſeeke his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. It is the meſſenger that <hi>Ezekias</hi> vſed to haue the charter of his dares renued:<note place="margin">Eſay. 38.3 2. Kings. 4.32. Math. 5.7.</note> that <hi>Eliſha</hi> vſed to haue the Sunamites childes ſoule renued: that the ſicke of the <hi>palſey</hi> vſed to haue his hands, and feete renued, and that <hi>Dauid</hi> vſed to haue his heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued. It is prayer, the language of heauen, the tongue of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Austin in Soliloq.</note> the ſpeech of <hi>Zyon,</hi> the muſick of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the harmony of ſinners, the melody of Saints. It is that fire which being kindled by the ſpirit of God, in the Temple of the ſoule, will euer burne vpon the Altar of the heart, and euer aſcend from the cenſor of the Tongue, till thou haſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned of God the petition of <hi>Dauid,</hi> Create in me a new, cleane, pure, vndefiled, vncorrupted heart.<note place="margin">Diuiſio.</note> I will onely inſiſt vpon theſe two parts; firſt the greatneſſe of his ſuite;<note place="margin">Duae partes.</note> no purgation, or clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or curing, or recouering, or quickning, but a new creating; <hi>Create in mee.</hi> Secondly, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his ſore &amp; ſorrow, not his hand, or foot, or eye, or head, only ill affected, but his heart, the beſt member, the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of his ſoule, <hi>Create in mee a new heart.</hi> And of theſe briefly, praying as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> did on the like occaſion, <hi>Deus faciet hunc textum tam commodum quam accommodatum.</hi> God make this text ſo commodious for our ſoules, as accommodated for theſe our times. And firſt for the Creation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15622:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prima. pars. Hoſiod. Ouid. Plato. vide Phillip. Mornay lib. <hi>10</hi> de vera Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one. Tull de Nat. Deor.</note>The Creation is the Geneſis of the booke of God, the firſt Act in Nature, as Heathens confeſſe, the firſt ouerture of Gods power, as Diuines wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a worke ſo wonderfull, that the Atheiſt inquireth of <hi>Plato, quae ferramenta, qui vectes, quae mollitiones, quae machinae, tanti operis fuerunt,</hi> what were the Engins, poſts, machinations, pullyes, leauers, pillers, ſcaffolds, of ſo great and wonderfull a worke.</p>
            <p>Who can imagine that ſo many things, diuerſe in quality, immenſe in quantity, high in ſublimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, deepe in profundity, could euer bee made: that ſo many ſinews and ioynts, and connexions and con-catenations ſhould bee ſo orderly diſpoſed in that great Fabrique: <hi>Naſci,</hi> to be borne is a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, a body though little, to bee ſo framed, the ioynts to mooue ſo actiuely, the ſinews to ſtirre ſo nimbly, ſences to vtter force ſo ſharply, the lungs to breath ſo powerfully,<note place="margin">Iob.</note> it drew <hi>Iob</hi> into ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, and to aske who hath framed thee in the wombe? but to bee <hi>Created,</hi> a world ſo maſſy, ſo mighty, vnleſſe man looke with the eyes of Grace, through the windowes of Nature, hee cannot as a naturall man perceiue it: but <hi>Moyſes</hi> taught it,<note place="margin">Plato Moſes, Atticus. <hi>Gen. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Plato</hi> learned it, and though the <hi>Atheist</hi> do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, yet in the firſt of Geneſis, in the Capitall Characters of Heauen and Earth it is deſcribed, and ſome vnder-take to free <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> from deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Creation, though his workes do much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne it, hee being as ambitious to ouer-come all
<pb facs="tcp:15622:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>other opinions, as his Scholler <hi>Alexander</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer other Nations.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Create,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquiuas.</note> in Scripture is taken by the Schoolemen &amp; Fathers diuerſly, <hi>pro prefectione ex nihilo,</hi> In the Image of God he created man: <hi>pro generatione ex propria ſubſtantia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1.27.</note> Theſe are the generations of the Heauen and the Earth, as in Geneſis.<note place="margin">Gen. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Pro renouatione,</hi> as in <hi>Eſay.</hi> I will Create a new Heauen,<note place="margin">Eſay. 65.17.</note> and a new Earth; <hi>pro donorum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus infuſione,</hi> as in the <hi>Epheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns.</hi> Created by his ſpirit to good workes:<note place="margin">Ier. 31.22.</note> 
               <hi>pro filij Dei incarnatione,</hi> as in <hi>Ieremy,</hi> The Lord hath created a new thing, a woman ſhall compaſſe a man. And in this place <hi>pro regeneratione,</hi> as ſome, <hi>pro iuſtificatione,</hi> as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Improperly it is vſed many wayes, as either that in our Anniuerſary Act and Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Vniuerſities, <hi>the Creation of our Doctors:</hi> or as at this feaſt the word is vſed for the Royall inueſtiture and Creation of the moſt noble Prince. But to returne to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Regeneration</hi> may fitly bee called a <hi>Creation;</hi> In the one, the other is ſhadowed: In <hi>praedeſtination</hi> the huge and vaſt deepe, the darke forme whereof can hardly be diſcerned: In <hi>vocation,</hi> the ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of light from darkneſſe, of knowledge, from ignorance in the ſoule. In <hi>iuſtification</hi> the Sunne is created, the beames of grace begin to ſhine. In <hi>glorification,</hi> the new <hi>Adam</hi> is framed after the image of God, and placed in the Paradiſe of immortality: <hi>Dauid</hi> had taſted of theſe riuers
<pb facs="tcp:15622:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Paradiſe, he had beene praedeſtinated, called, iuſtified, but now theſe ſtreames and currents were dryed vp, his forme was in a <hi>chaos,</hi> his ſunne in a cloud, folly had polluted his eyes, filth had poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his thoughts, bloud had defiled his hands, ſhame had couered his head, ſinne had prophaned his heart, not onely, no whole part in his body, but no whole part in his ſoule, no meanes to cure him, to create him a new. There was a time when he cryed out <hi>Concaluit cor, et exardeſcit ignis,</hi> my heart is hotte,<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.3. <hi>Auſt. in Pſal.</hi>
               </note> and the fire is kindled within mee. But now his heart is cold, the fire is quenched, the ſpirit is departed, his ſoule is expired, and he is euen as a dead man, <hi>Corpus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane animae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of <hi>Hermotinus</hi> it is recounted that hee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times loſt his ſoule, that it would depart from him at times, and come home againe: ſuch was <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtate, he was in a trance, not a ſlumber alone, but a ſtrange Lethargie: <hi>Ionas</hi> that ſlept ſo faſt, when the waues, windes, ſtormes, out-cryes of the Saylers, ſtretchings of the tacklings, the Sea, the ſhip, the Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s could not awake him: <hi>Dauid</hi> ſlept as ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly as he did, dayes, weekes, moneths, a whole yeare, he had in the courſe of his life many enemies; <hi>Saul</hi> warring, <hi>Shemei</hi> rayling, <hi>Doeg</hi> intrapping, <hi>Philiſtins</hi> betraying, <hi>Abſolon</hi> rebelling, <hi>Adoniah</hi> vſurping, but all theſe not ſo great, as the two enemies that had ſet now vpon him, beſieged him, boorded him, poſſeſſed him, adultery and murther: adultery had
<pb facs="tcp:15622:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>adulterated his ſoule, and murther had almoſt murthered his heart: hee was almoſt in that ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull ſtate that Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> deſcribeth a hardned hart,<note place="margin">Bernard ad Eugenium.</note> which be it extimulated and exulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated neuer ſo much, yet will not be cut with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction, nor ſoftened with loue, nor moued with mercy, nor allured with intreaty, yeeldeth not to threatnings, vnthankfull for benefits, vnfaithfull in Counſels, vnmercifull in iudgments, ſhameleſſe in diſhoneſty, wretchleſſe in danger, in things aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to men voide of humanity, in matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God full of temerity, vnmindfull of what is paſt, negligent of what is preſent, improuident of what is to come. Such almoſt was this heart of <hi>Dauid,</hi> as ſecureles, and careleſſe as any hart could be: Idleneſſe had vſhered Concupiſcence, Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and blood reuel'd in his Court, nay in his heart, in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vileneſſe of his thoughts, hatefull to God, nor the filthineſſe of his mind, hurtfull to himſelfe, nor the ſight of his ſubiects, nor the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of his ſeruants, nor the blood of <hi>Vriah,</hi> nor the great belly of <hi>Bethſheba,</hi> nor the crying of thoſe two curſed twins, Adulterie, and Murther, could cauſe him to feare, till that <hi>Nathan</hi> had rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, and the new ſpirit had created him.</p>
            <p>No maruaile, though <hi>Pharoah</hi> adde ſinne vnto ſinne,<note place="margin">Exod. 10.20. Mat. 2.16.</note> or <hi>Herod</hi> ioyne maſſacre to ambition, or <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> ioyne pride vnto bloud,<note place="margin">Dan 5.27.</note> or <hi>Nero</hi> ioyne villanie to miſchiefe, or <hi>Catiline</hi> ſerue to ioyne ruine to ryot, or the <hi>wicked</hi> ioyne the cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropes
<pb facs="tcp:15622:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>of iniquity to the cords of vanitie, when the bowels of Gods elect, ſhall be ſo filled &amp; poſſeſſed with careleſneſſe. What ſhall refraine the wicked from ſinning deſperately as <hi>Cain,</hi> rebelliouſly as <hi>Saul,</hi> preſumptuouſly as <hi>Pharoah,</hi> aſpiringly as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer,</hi> trecherouſly as <hi>Iudas:</hi> when <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods owne heart, his Pſalmodiſt, his Organiſt, his Prophet, his ſweeteſt ſinger of Iſrael, ſhould ſo offend the God of Iſrael, and need ſuch a transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation?</p>
            <p>But the doctrine herein for vs all, is this,<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> that though the godly may be in a traunce for a time, and the fit of that ſinfull feauer ſo ſtrongly handle them, yet the Lord hath a mind to releeue them, and a power to reuiue them. <hi>Dauid</hi> had the <hi>Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique</hi> of this <hi>Theorique,</hi> in all his ſoundings he ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the well of <hi>Bethel,</hi> flieth to the cittie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, the Wel of Gods fauour, the cittie of Gods power, he remembred euen now, when his ſoule is brought to the vttermoſt pit, nethermoſt hell, yet by his reſpiration, by Gods inſpiration there is life in him, he ſigheth out, and groneth out, <hi>Create in me a new heart.</hi> That, as in the <hi>Acts</hi> when <hi>Eutiches,</hi> ouercome with ſleepe, fell downe from the third loft, <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake, <hi>Trouble not your ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.10.</note> 
               <hi>for his life is in him:</hi> ſo may I ſpeak vnto you all, <hi>Right Reuerend, Right Honorable, and Welbeloued, that he are me this day,</hi> though ye haue ſeene <hi>Dauid</hi> in his folly, in his fall, &amp; that Scripture hath vncouered his nakednes ſo far, that he ſeemeth to be dead and buried, and to
<pb facs="tcp:15622:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſmell in the graue, as the Fathers expound that of <hi>Lazarus</hi> 4. daies;<note place="margin">Auſtin Ambroſ.</note> the 1. day by conceiuing finne, the 2. by conſenting, the 3. day by comitting, the 4. day, by continuing in ſin, yet there is life in him, and as <hi>Dauid</hi> was a type of Chriſt, ſo the words ſpoken of Chriſt may be true of <hi>Dauid, He was dead, but is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue,</hi> and he ſhall liue for euermore: for whom God loueth, he loueth vnto the end: all the deuils in hel, all infernall complices cannot raze one of Gods ſeruants out of <hi>the booke of life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 1.18.</note> None of them ſhal be loſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.12.</note> though the ſownings of their faith cauſe them ſometimes to draw their breath ſo inwardly to it ſelf, that no man can perceiue it, yet the good nes of God ſhall embrace the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Eutiches,</hi> their life in them,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.9.</note> their ſeed is in them. <hi>Salomon</hi> in the trance of Idolatrie, <hi>Ionas</hi> in the trance of recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſancie, <hi>Ieremy</hi> in the trance of impatiency, <hi>Peter</hi> in the trance of apoſtacie, <hi>Thomas</hi> in the trance of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie, God ſhall in theſe haue a bleſſed purpoſe, both to ſuch as are in theſe ſpirituall <hi>Apoplexies,</hi> and to others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ireneus</hi> giueth 3.<note place="margin">Ireneus.</note> reaſons in reſpect of vs, why the infirmity of the Saints are Chronicled in the book of God: 1. to giue vs warning, that both they and we haue but one God, who was euer offended with ſinne, how great ſoeuer the perſons were that wrought it. 2. to teach vs to abſtaine from ſin: for if the ancient Patriarcks who went before vs, both in time promiſe, couenant, loue, &amp; grace of God, and for whom (ſins being yet not ſo many) the Son
<pb facs="tcp:15622:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God had not ſuffred, if they bare ſuch reproches among their poſterity, that their corruptions are regiſtred, what ſhall we ſuſtain, that liue in a brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and later age of the world, and haue continued beyond the comming of the Lord Ieſus. 3. to giue vs warning and inſtruction, that there was a cure behind, the ſacrifice of the Lambe which was not then ſlaine but for ſuch as ſin now, Chriſt dieth no more, no more ſufferings, no more ſatisfactions. And as another well noteth, If that an apple, a wedge, a bribe, the turning back of the eye in <hi>Lots</hi> wife, ſmile of the countenance in <hi>Abrahams</hi> wife, diſcontent once in <hi>Miriam,</hi> falſe fire once in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> and the like, if theſe deſerued ſuch puniſhment, what ſhall our cuſtomary ſins, open and ſecret, of the eye and hand, in word, in works priuate within our owne tent, publike to the great Eye of heauen.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auſten</hi> handling the point vpon this Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auſtin.</hi> in Pſa 51.</note> maketh this enarration, <hi>Commiſſum atque conſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt,</hi> it is done and written, not for thy imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but for thy inſtruction, to informe thee thus much, that if thou takeſt the wings of the morning, &amp; fly from one end of the earth to the other, thou canſt not find a ſoule ſo pure that hath not ſind, the chiefeſt, greateſt, ſtrongeſt, wiſeſt, goodlieſt, godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, haue fallen; Patriarckes, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, Confeſſors, ſtars, Angels, al haue ſinned, yea and ſome ſo fallen, that they neuer roſe again: ſinne thou not, that thou maiſt riſe; but ſo riſe from ſin, that thou maiſt neuer fal againe. Feare, O feare
<pb facs="tcp:15622:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>the fall, ſwallow not the hooke of delight, <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia, contriſt ans ſcientia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard in Cant.</note> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> doth etymologize the word, Conſcience will follow, if ſin be the Prologue, ſhame wil be the Epilogue, the woorme, the whip, the ſcourge of conſcience will feare thee, ſhe is marked and obſerued by her owne eye, though no other eye perceiue her, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and chaſed by her owne foote, though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in heauen or earth purſue her, ſhee fleeth, feareth, and yet ſtingeth and fretteth, and hath a thouſand witneſſes within her owne breaſt when ſhe is free from all the world: Happy then if the conſcience finding her miſery, ſeeke the promiſe, the promiſe take hold on faith, faith aske prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, praier aske God, that God heare, and mercy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that againe, <hi>we may be created in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the daies of our liues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Triplex Creatio ſpiritualis.</note>This <hi>Creation</hi> is ſpiritually wrought, firſt by Baptiſme, the character of Chriſtians, marke of the Church, ſigne of the Choſen, oth of the Saints, liuery of the Seruants, aſſurance of the Sons of God, <hi>A peccato mundans, Poenam relaxans, rationalem illuminens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Albertus in Comp. Theol. Euſebius.</note> 
               <hi>Concupiſcibilem ad bonum inflammans, Characterem inueniens,</hi> as <hi>Ratisbonen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> collecteth the power and vertue hereof. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> neuer Baptiſed before hee was dying, and <hi>Dauid</hi> neuer ſo baptiſed as heere, when he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt dead and then in his laſt gaſpe, <hi>waſh me, clenſe me, purge me.</hi> Neuer any a more true knight of the Bath then he, hee had the waters of Iordan,
<pb facs="tcp:15622:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>pooles of Shiloan, fountaines of Lebanon, ſprings for the Spring, and fall of the leafe: But our <hi>Baptiſme</hi> doth create vs anew, no ſacrifice or ſacrament of the old law ſo powerfull, they were but remembrances gratulatory, no oblation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priatory, but this ſo energeticall as that the forme and frame, ſoule and body bee changed: It is the great ſeale of the Charter of heauen which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed <hi>Omnibus Christi fide libus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gratia gratis data. Gratia gratum faciens. Gratia prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaen. Gratia ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens.</note> To all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people of the world.</p>
            <p>Secondly wee are Created by <hi>Grace, Grace</hi> is ſhed into our hearts. The diſtinctions of <hi>Grace</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Schoolemen</hi> will be harſh to many in this aſſembly, but all muſt know that in this wee muſt acknowledge with the Prophet, <hi>Grace, Grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zechariah. 13.1</note> 
               <hi>all is Grace, euen that fountaine opened to the houſe of</hi> Dauid. For our righteouſneſſe cannot <hi>Create</hi> vs, no more then we can <hi>Create</hi> it, for had we <hi>Iuſtitiam Gentilium,</hi> it were but vaine and Philoſophicall, had we <hi>Iuſtitiam Phariſaeorum,</hi> it were but ſhadowy and legall, had wee onely <hi>Iuſtitiam Viatoris,</hi> it were but imperfect, and caſuall, no ſparke of our owne can enflame vs, onely <hi>Grace</hi> can <hi>Create</hi> vs: A ſweeter word then <hi>Grace</hi> was neuer vttered, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riams</hi> Tabrel, <hi>Aſaphs</hi> Trumpet, <hi>Ieduthun</hi> his Negi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noth, <hi>Dauid</hi> his Cimballs, <hi>Salomons</hi> Songs, the <hi>Spouſes</hi> ſonnets, neuer made ſweeter melody, then this beloued voice of the beloued GRACE. It is the <hi>Balme</hi> that runneth from the head to the beard, and from the beard vnto the skirts
<pb facs="tcp:15622:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the garment, it is <hi>Iordan</hi> that maketh glad the City of God, it is the roabe of righteouſneſſe that couereth the whole man, &amp; God giueth liberally thereof to euery one, <hi>Gratiam dat, datam conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat, conſeuatam multiplicat, multiplicatam remu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> giueth <hi>Grace,</hi> freely, conſerueth <hi>Grace</hi> giuen, multiplieth <hi>Grace</hi> conſerued, and rewardeth <hi>Grace</hi> multiplied. <hi>Creati ſumus per gratiam,</hi> we are Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by grace.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Creati ſumus per poenitentiam,</hi> wee are Created againe by Repentance, it is the ſpring of the life of man, the budding of the figge tree, the reuiuing of the withered lilly,<note place="margin">Plyn. Nat. Hiſtor.</note> that as the <hi>Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> reneweth ſight, the <hi>Eagle</hi> reneweth youth, the <hi>Hart</hi> reneweth ſtrength,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103,5</note> ſo <hi>Man</hi> by repentance caſteth of the ſinne that preſſeth downe, and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>Created</hi> and reſtored, purged, waſhed, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Creation</hi> requireth many conditions as the Fathers obſerue:<note place="margin">Aust. in <hi>Pſal.</hi> Alber. de ſacr.</note> for Repentance muſt bee <hi>tota,</hi> wholy, with all the heart. Secondly, <hi>Amara,</hi> bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, make lamentation,<note place="margin">Ioel 2, 12 Ier 6, 26 Wiſdom 6.18</note> and bitter mourning. Thirdly, <hi>Voluntaria,</hi> voluntary, come freely, and willingly vnto the Lord. Fourthly it muſt be <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celerata,</hi> ſpeedy,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5, 3 Cant. 5, 3</note> deferre not to pay that which thou haſt paied vnto God. And fiftly it muſt be <hi>Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nua,</hi> continuall and perſeuerant, if thou haſt put put off thy coate how ſhalt thou put it on? If thou haue waſhed thy feet how ſhalt thou defile them? Thus obſeruing the conditions &amp; binding
<pb facs="tcp:15622:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>thy ſelfe by this obligation thou ſhalt be <hi>Created</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> was.</p>
            <p>If wee ſhould looke vpon him, when he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the ſheepfolds, from following the <hi>Ewes</hi> great with young, from being ſo meane in his brothers eyes, nay in his owne eyes, euen then when his fathers houſe was of the pooreſt in the Tribe, him-ſelfe the leaſt of his family, loweſt of brethren, and if after wee ſhall behold him aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from being a Shepheard to follow ſheepe, to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Homer.</note> a ſhepheard to gouerne and lead people, from being the meaneſt of his bretheren, to bee Lord, and then to change his coate for a Court, his ſheep-hooke for a Scepter, to become wiſer then his teachers, greater then his enemies, more puiſant then <hi>Saul,</hi> more victorious then <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> more honoured then the Aged; this in the eye of man was a new <hi>Creation,</hi> but yet not to bee compared with this: Then his ſtate was changed from poore to riche, now his ſoule is changed from ſinfull to a ſanctified ſtate. And being ſo <hi>Created</hi> againe, the words of the Pſalme may fitte him, <hi>O well is thee, and happy ſhalt thou bee, thou art fairer then the children of men, full of grace are thy lips, becauſe God hath bleſſed thee for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe of this is to direct vs to a due regarde of our corruption,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> who haue neede ſo to bee refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in our liues: and yet in this conſideration euen to behold the mercy ſeate, the throane of grace, from whence by the powerfull operation
<pb facs="tcp:15622:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>Gods ſpirit</hi> we may be created. <hi>Vides miſeriam agnoſce miſericordiam:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> dooſt thou behold thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, acknowledge Gods mercy euer able to change thee, and to purge thee from actuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauations, and natural corruptions, from thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, mighty, heauy, filthy, bloudy, crying ſinnes: and therefore to call frequently to God, to pray hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily for this reformation, to pray that wee may powre in our prayers:<note place="margin">Solinus.</note> for as the ſtone <hi>Diacletes</hi> is ſaid to looſe all her excellent power and operation if put into the mouth of a dead man, ſo <hi>Prayer</hi> if put into a mans mouth whoſe heart is dead, or whoſe hand is vncleane, it looſeth all the ſoueraine properties. Some of the Fathers haue deciphered the three Theologicall vertues of faith, hope, and charity, by the three that attended Chriſt at the tranſfiguration on the Mount, and at his ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the garden, <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn; Peter</hi> by faith, <hi>Iames</hi> by hope, <hi>Iohn</hi> by loue: If thou didſt imagine thy ſelfe to haue all theſe three, and hadſt not the power of <hi>Prayer,</hi> it were nothing: Not to ſpeake of the efficacie of hope or loue, the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of faith be many, to remoue mountaines, to quench the fire, to ſtay the windes, to reſiſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: <hi>Prayer</hi> hath all theſe, it remooueth moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, thy ſinnes bee as Mountaines before the Throne of GOD, it remooueth them fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from thee, then the Eaſt is from the Weſt, it quencheth fire, if the fire of luſt kindle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thee, by <hi>Prayer</hi> thou mayeſt quench thee, if
<pb facs="tcp:15622:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>the windy ſtorme of any deiected deſperat thought do blow within thee, pray vp, <hi>Lord let thy enemies bee ſcattered:</hi> if the Diuell, world, and fleſh, ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, yet by this thou ſhalt put to flight all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall complices. It opened and ſhut heauen, it brought plenty and dearth, drought and raine, and will if thou bee acquainted with her, be the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt companion that euer accompanied any on the face of the earth, to ſay no more, it will preferre thee, and <hi>create</hi> thee heire apparant of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen.</p>
            <p>The feſtiuity of the <hi>Creation</hi> now celebrated, ſhould infuſe greater ſpirits into vs then hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſuch occaſions of ioy to vs, of happineſſe for vs, ſuch triumphes, applauſes, Iubilees as theſe, do draw from vs gratulation and acclamation, in that <hi>God hath not onely giuen his iudgements vnto the King, but his righteouſneſse to the Kings ſonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">72.1.</note> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuch a hope for the young, ſuch a comfort for the old, ſuch happineſſe for all; ſuch a young <hi>Ptolomey</hi> for ſtudies and Libraries; ſuch a young <hi>Alexander</hi> for affecting martialiſme and chiualrie, ſuch a yong <hi>Ioſiah</hi> for religion &amp; piety. This ſhould ſtirre vs vp to acknowledgement of Gods mercies by his Highneſſe, and mooue vs to a ſpirituall ambition, for our owne happineſſe: That as in ſuch honorable ſtate he is to be created PRINCE of ſo great place here on earth, by <hi>his Purple robes, Sword, Signet, Golden Staffe,</hi> (the earneſts of his glorious and triumphant royalty in Heauen)
<pb facs="tcp:15622:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo ſeeing God hath <hi>Created vs Kings and Prieſts,</hi> as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Reu. 1.</note> we ſhould deſire the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of this ſpirituall <hi>Creation</hi> to put on the roabes of righteouſneſſe, the ſword of the ſpirit, to receiue the ſtaffe of protection, to be placed as ſignets on Gods hand.</p>
            <p>There was as Creation of a Prince in Scripture, but it was the pooreſt and meaneſt that euer was. The Prince his name is found in <hi>Eſay:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>The</hi> PRINCE <hi>of Peace,</hi> and of his creation mention is made in <hi>Ieremie: The Lord hath</hi> CREATED <hi>a new Thing on the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 31.22.</note> it was new indeed as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, <hi>a ſaeculo non est auditum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Temp.</note> neuer ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world was the like newes heard, and <hi>Bernard</hi> ſtood at an amazement at this <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. de Jncarnat.</note> there was <hi>Lux non lucem, verbum infans, aqua ſitiens, panis eſuriens:</hi> At that <hi>creation</hi> there was a light not ſhining, the word an infant not ſpeaking, the water of life thirſting, the bread of life hung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, God himſelfe deſcending, and the Creator Created, if I may ſo ſpeake. A body haſt thou Created ſaith the Pſalmiſt, a body without ſinne, to endure the ſuffrings for ſinne, and to vndergoe all the torments that the vnbounded inuention of hell could deuiſe: This was a new thing, <hi>Nouum et omnium nouitatum nouitas ſupereminens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerome.</note> ſaith <hi>Ierome,</hi> ſuch and ſo merueilous, miraculous &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary a nouelty as the world of worlds can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not yeeld the like preſident. Let the <hi>Sibills</hi> ſpeak of their new <hi>Rutilans Sydus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Ciuit. Dei.</note> the Aſtronomers of their
<pb facs="tcp:15622:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>new ſtarres <hi>in Cygno &amp; Serpentario,</hi> let the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries find out a new <hi>Vtopia,</hi> the Coſmographers their new-found <hi>America:</hi> let <hi>Pancirolla</hi> write whole volumes <hi>De nouis Repertis,</hi> and <hi>Mercurius Gallobelgicus</hi> (the worlds Poſt-maſter for newes) ſupply newes euery yere, yet no like newes to this, no <hi>Creation</hi> ſince the firſt <hi>Creation</hi> of the world like to this, the <hi>Court</hi> then to like in a <hi>poore Inne,</hi> the <hi>ſtable</hi> to be the <hi>bed-chamber,</hi> the <hi>cratch</hi> the Royall pallat; <hi>VVinter</hi> and <hi>Hunger</hi> to attend, and yet the <hi>VViſemen</hi> to offer, <hi>Angels</hi> to honour, <hi>Shepheards</hi> to ſing of him, <hi>Oracles</hi> then to ceaſe, <hi>Deuils</hi> then to tremble: this was a New, a ſtrange <hi>Creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To <hi>Zebedees</hi> children <hi>Chriſt</hi> anſwered, <hi>Ye cannot be baptized with the Baptiſme wherewith I must bee baptized:</hi> ſo I may ſay, wee would be loath to bee CREATED in that order, that he was CREATED. But let it be our morning and euening prayer, that we may be created according to his likeneſſe, that as he of <hi>God</hi> became man, ſo we of men may become the ſonnes of <hi>God.</hi> Delay not, it is daungerous; preſume not, it is perillous: <hi>Dauid</hi> ſought it and found it; vnleſſe thou ſeeke it with heartie prayer, thou maiſt ſeeke it and not find it:<note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> 
               <hi>Huic fit miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia, tibi non fit iniuria,</hi> though he ſhewed great mercie to <hi>Dauid,</hi> and will not to thee, he doth thee no iniurie. Take heed leaſt impenitencie cauſe him to prooue a wrath-reuenging <hi>God,</hi> and let no man continue in ſinne, that <hi>grace</hi> may abound: Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, Deuils can do no more, if any do ſo, he may
<pb facs="tcp:15622:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſleepe his euerlaſting ſleepe of ſinne, neuer be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, neuer be wakened more: God may ſay to thee as he ſaid to the Diſciples, and pronounce that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt thee for thy ſleepe of the ſoule, as he did to them for the ſleepe of the bodie: <hi>For hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ſleepe and take thy reſt, till thy eyes ſinke into the holes of thy head, I will neuer come, nor ſend, nor call, nor waken thee, the night ſhall compaſſe thee, and the pit ſhall ſhut her mouth vpon thee.</hi> In our Church Lyturgie, which is in theſe daies like to <hi>Christ</hi> crucified between two, there is a moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable promiſe drawne from Scripture, <hi>At what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent of his ſinnes from the bottome of his heart, God will put away all his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe out of his remembrance:</hi> thereupon many take their pleaſure, and glut themſelues with ſinne, referre all good thoughts till the laſt houre, neuer put their hands into their boſome, to ſee how lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous they be, their mouthes continue to bee the vents to breath forth the putrified ſauour of their ſoule, their eyes the windowes, their eares the doores of deſtruction, their vnderſtandings flaues to their willes, their wils common curtizans of pollution, their memories the table-booke of their corruptions. O miſerable and fearefull ſtate of ſuch! If any at any time, in any caſe had reaſon to crie with <hi>Dauid,</hi> theſe haue <hi>[Create in me a new heart.]</hi> And ſo much of the firſt part, <hi>Create in mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The part to be <hi>created,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secunda pars.</note> is the heart, <hi>[Create in
<pb facs="tcp:15622:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>me a new heart]</hi> As is gold among the mettalls, the ſight among the ſenſes, the Nerue Opticke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſinewes, ſo is the heart among the members, and yet of the heart <hi>Ieremy</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, <hi>The heart of man is deceitfull and wicked aboue all things, who can know it, Ier.</hi> 17.9. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the heart be ſo little, as that it will ſcarce ſerue a Kite for a baite, yet the windings and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings in the heart containe many <hi>Maeanders.</hi> The Heathens accounted it the Sunne of the bodie: for as in the middeſt of Heauen the Sunne is ſituated, which enlighteneth all things with his rayes, and cheriſheth the world, and the things therein contained with his life-keeping heate, ſo the heart of man, the fountaine of life and heate, hath aſſigned to it by nature, the midle part of the bodie for his habitation, from whence proceedeth life and heate vnto all the parts of the bodie, as it were into riuers, whereby they bee preſerued and enabled to performe their naturall function. In Diuinitie wee ſhall finde it to bee <hi>Sacram Palladis arcem,</hi> the ſeate of reaſon, the Metropolis of the ſoule,<note place="margin">Andr. Laur.</note> the Sanctuarie of the mind, the Arke of the vnderſtanding, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of faith, the holy Place of the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> ſo that with a good heart there is euer a wiſe tongue, a diligent hand, a warie foote, a watchfull eye, an attentiue eare, and a humble minde, this beeing like the great wheele in a watch, all the leſſer depend vpon it, the tongue wil not praiſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:15622:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>the heart do loue the eare will not heare, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the heart do mind: the hand will not giue, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the heart do pittie: the foote will not go, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the heart do ſtriue: the heart like the Iudge giueth the charge; like the Captaine giueth the onſet: it is the warning peece of the caſtell: when the heart is prepared, the ſenſes ate readie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, the imagination to repreſent, the knowledge to forme, the wit to find out, the reaſon to iudge, the memorie to conſerue, the vnderſtanding to apprehend, and ſo of all the other faculties.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> defineth the heart to be the ſeate of the ſoule, and the ſoule to be the whole inward man, wherewith the maſſe of clay is quickened and gouerned, and held together, changing her names according to her ſundrie offices which ſhe beareth in the bodie: when ſhe quickeneth the bodie, ſhee is called the ſoule: when ſhe deſireth any thing, the will: for knowledge, the mind: for recordation, the memorie: for giuing life, the ſpirit: for apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding outwardly the ſenſe. All ſtarres receiue light from the Sunne, ſo that if the light be darke, how great is this darkneſſe. In the Temple there was the Altar and the Cenſor; a Chriſtian muſt haue both; the Cenſor is the tongue, it poliſheth the beſt operations of the ſenſes, and is the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, Speaker, Interpreter, between God and man: but the heart, the Altar, is of more honour: for howſoeuer the <hi>Romaines</hi> ſo much honoured the hand, and <hi>Eſop</hi> preferred the tongue, and the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes
<pb facs="tcp:15622:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>the eye, and the Anatomiſts the head, yet <hi>God</hi> of all other parts deſireth the heart: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo much prayeth for the <hi>Creating of a heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The languiſhments of the bodie be nothing to the ſoule: as the ſoule is in compariſon of the bodie full of glorie, ſo is the griefe of the ſoule more full of inward miſerie, and therefore the hazard of the ſoule more to be feared, and the ſafetie of the heart more to be tendred. In the greateſt diſtemperature of <hi>Dauid,</hi> when his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die was ſo ill affected,<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.2.</note> no health in his fleſh, no reſt in his bones, his loynes filled with a ſore diſeaſe, his wounds putrified and ſtunke, the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and moiſture quite dryed vp, when he was almoſt diſſolued into the duſt of death, yet his ſoule might haue beene ſafe and ſound: but if the ſoule be ſicke, can the bodie haue any comfort? it was ill with thoſe that cryed out in Scripture, <hi>My head, my head:</hi> and another, <hi>My belly, my belly,</hi> but when they cry out of the heart, of the ſoule, all will be out of tune.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Italian</hi> obſerueth by a Prouerbe, that the <hi>Germans</hi> wittes dwell in their fingers end; and ſo muſt all true goodneſſe, it muſt haue a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent from the heart to the hand: for when the heart doth indite a good matter, the hand will eaſily bee the penne of a readie writer.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Anatomiſts</hi> obſerue, that there bee ſtrings that paſſe from the heart to the tongue,
<pb facs="tcp:15622:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſo what the heart thinketh the tongue vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, then the eare heareth, the eye obſerueth, the tongue prayeth, ſingeth, praiſeth, recordeth: and howſoeuer the tongue be in the higheſt part of the bodie, and yet is the ſpeaker of the lower houſe, it deliuereth onely that which the nobler parts haue agreed to, nothing but that which the hart and the faculties of the ſoule haue determined. And as all good commeth from the heart, ſo all good that commeth to vs, commeth into the heart: it is the Schoole Maxime, <hi>Virtutes Theologicae non ſunt in nob is per acquiſitionem, ſed per infuſionem,</hi> the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of the head cannot obtaine faith, hope, charitie, it muſt be the infuſion into the heart: for as <hi>Biel</hi> teacheth of faith, <hi>Fides eſt non ſuaſa ſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirata,</hi> not perſwaded, but inſpired: ſo of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Theologicall vertues, and of euery good and perfect gift it is infuſed by the Father of light into the heart. So that God dwelleth in the ſoule, and the ſoule dwelleth as in his <hi>Metropolis,</hi> in the hart. And this cauſed <hi>Dauid</hi> to require <hi>the new heart, the good heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The doctrine hence proceeding is, that a good Chriſtian muſt euer pray, and ſtudy, to keepe his heart vndefiled; and if it chaunce to bee neuer ſo little polluted, preſently to waſh it, to cleanſe it: for the heart is the inner ſide that is to be purged, it is the Parlour where the <hi>Sauiour</hi> will eate the <hi>Paſseouer,</hi> it is the <hi>Gedeons fleece, the Goſhen, the Chanaan, the Temple, the Sanctum
<pb facs="tcp:15622:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sanctorum of the Temple.</hi> It is the inner roome, the Treaſurie, the Tower, the Arke; here dwelleth zeale, of <hi>Elias,</hi> for zeale in Chriſtianitie is <hi>ignis ſanctus:</hi> next zeale dwelleth knowledge, of S. <hi>Paul;</hi> for zeale without knowledge is <hi>ignis fatuus:</hi> here dwelleth faithfulneſſe, as in the <hi>Paſtor</hi> of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> for faithfulneſſe to the truth is <hi>ſuffimentum redo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens:</hi> and next faithfulneſſe dwelleth charitie, as in Saint <hi>Iohn;</hi> for faithfulneſſe without charitie, is <hi>ſuffitus non redolens, ſed olens:</hi> here dwelleth pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, as in the <hi>Niniuites;</hi> for practiſe is <hi>stella lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens:</hi> next practiſe dwelleth perſeuerance as the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians;</hi> for practiſe without perſeuerance, is but <hi>Stella cadens:</hi> here dwelleth beleefe in God as in the <hi>Diſciples;</hi> for beleefe in Chriſtianitie, is <hi>lucerna ardens:</hi> next beleefe dwels loue in God, as in the <hi>Pſalmiſt;</hi> for beleefe without loue, is <hi>Cymbalu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tinni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens:</hi> here dwelleth obedience as in <hi>Abraham;</hi> for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is <hi>virga conſolans:</hi> next obedience dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth patience, as in <hi>Iob;</hi> for obedience without pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, is <hi>baculus non dirigens.</hi> In a word, in this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe is the tree which <hi>Hugo</hi> deſcribeth, <hi>Arbor bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis quae per timorem ſeminatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hugo de San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto victore.</note> the tree of goodneſſe which is ſet by <hi>feare,</hi> ſtrengthened by <hi>faith,</hi> watered by <hi>grace,</hi> germinated by <hi>godlines,</hi> will waxe greene by <hi>hope,</hi> will fructifie by <hi>loue,</hi> will build by <hi>learning,</hi> will bloſſom by <hi>long-continuing,</hi> will grow ripe by <hi>patience,</hi> and the fruite of <hi>life</hi> will be gathered at <hi>death,</hi> the fruite of grace now, and of glorie hereafter; for theſe differ, but, <hi>Tempore
<pb facs="tcp:15622:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; loco,</hi> but in time and place, as the Schoolemen ſpeake: then euery honeſt vnmasked Chriſtian may ſay as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, <hi>Cor meum dilataſti,</hi> thou haſt expatiated my heart, a great doore is open, and here dwell <hi>mercie,</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>ioy</hi> in the <hi>holy Ghoſt.</hi> In ſuch a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied heart, there dwels not the affectation of the titles of the world, which bee but <hi>follia terrae,</hi> the liueleſſe leaues of the earth; or the deſire of the fortunes of the world, which bee <hi>Lollia terrae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> the emptie windie chaffe of the earth; or the earneſt ſeeking for the wealth of the world, which be but <hi>Illia terrae,</hi> the exenterated guttes, and garbage of the earth; or the proſecution of the pleaſures of the earth, which be but <hi>Lillia terrae,</hi> the fading, falling, failing, ſtrawing-flowers of the earth. All theſe haue not habitation or commoration here; the good HEART (with Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>) counteth them ſhadowes, and in accounting them ſo, it thinkes too well of them: for there is much excellent Arte in delineating a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe: or it thinketh them dreames,<note place="margin">A Elian. hiſtor.</note> and ſleeps,<note place="margin">Chryſost.</note> as <hi>Chryſoſtome;</hi> and this thought is alſo too good; for in ſleepes there bee much eaſe and ſweete comfort: or holdeth them with <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach</hi> to bee ſmoakes, and that cenſure alſo is too good for them, for in incenſe there is ſweete ſauour in ſmoakes: or further with <hi>Nazianzene,</hi> calleth them follies, and this, as the reſt, is too good a name for them: for <hi>Eraſmus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:15622:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>wrote much in the praiſe of Folly. And therefore vpon little aduiſe, concludeth with <hi>Saint Paul,</hi> that they bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Stercora,</hi> dung, and filth, and ſtench, <hi>Adams</hi> Apple, <hi>Eſaus</hi> broth,<note place="margin">Philip. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Babilons</hi> Cuppe, <hi>Iudas</hi> ſoppe, the Sorcerers Serpents, the Spiders webbe, the Cocatrices Egges, the waters of <hi>Tema,</hi> which in a moiſture ſwell, &amp; in a drought faile: All theſe cannot fill the heart; <hi>Orontius</hi> deſcribeth the world in the forme of a Hart, and leaueth many ſpaces voide in the figure of the Hart, that cannot be filled vp with the world, for a Circle cannot fill vp a Triangle, ſo that <hi>the heart is more then all the world;</hi> nothing can fill the heart but God; the parts of the heart be a <hi>Trinary,</hi> and nothing can fill vp this <hi>Trinary,</hi> but the three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the <hi>Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> mencioneth a vaine heart, <hi>Eſay</hi> a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren heart, <hi>Ieremy</hi> a deceitfull heart, the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> a ſinfull heart, <hi>Paul</hi> a double heart, <hi>Moſes</hi> a hard heart: But <hi>Dauid</hi> deſireth <hi>the new, the cleane heart,</hi> When the Sunne riſeth, then the beaſts ariſe from their dens, the Fowles from their neſts, and men from their beds. So when the <hi>Heart</hi> ſetteth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, all the members will follow, nothing will ſtay after the <hi>Heart,</hi> but as the eyes of ſeruants looke to the hands of their Maiſters, and the eyes of hand-maides to their miſtreſſe, ſo the members of the body waite vpon the <hi>heart,</hi> vntill the Lord haue mercy vpon vs, and therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpake, Make cleane within in the <hi>heart,</hi> and all will bee
<pb facs="tcp:15622:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>cleane;<note place="margin">Math. 13.26. Luke.</note> and therefore the <hi>Publicane</hi> beate vpon his <hi>heart</hi> as if hee were angry that it waked not all the reſt: therefore <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, Make melody to the Lord in your <hi>hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 5.19.</note> ſhewing that the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers make a ſweete harmony, when the <hi>heart</hi> is in tune; and therefore <hi>Salomon,</hi> Gods Purueyor, cryeth for the <hi>heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Pilate</hi> had waſhed his <hi>heart</hi> when hee wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his hands,<note place="margin">Math. 27.42.</note> hee had beene as cleane as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman</hi> comming out of <hi>Iordan:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kings 5.</note> If the <hi>Siche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> had circumciſed their <hi>hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34.22.</note> when they cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed their fleſh, they had ſaued their ſoules when they loſt their liues.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.2.</note> If <hi>Caine</hi> had offered his <hi>heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.20.</note> when hee offered his fruites, his offring had beene as acceptable as <hi>Abels:</hi> If the <hi>Phariſey</hi> had lookt into the in-ſide, as well as to the out-ſide, his <hi>heart</hi> had beene as cleane as his hands. It is not enough to ſay my <hi>foote</hi> ſtandeth vpright,<note place="margin">Pſal 26.12. Pſal. 88.9. Pſal. 25.15. Pſal. 108.1. Pſal. 42.1.</note> or my <hi>hands</hi> I ſtretch foorth towards thy holy Temple, or mine <hi>eyes</hi> are euer toward the Lord: or mine <hi>eares</hi> O Lord haſt thou opened: or O God my <hi>Tongue</hi> is prepared. But as the HEART deſireth the water-brooke, ſo longeth my HART after thee O GOD, ſo beeing renued in heart, the heart ſhall bee capable of a new Soule: the Soule of a new body; that body of a new garment, that garment of a new girdle: And the Chriſtian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo altered, and changed, and reformed, and CREATED a new, GOD will manifeſt to him thoſe new things in <hi>Eſay;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 42.9. Ier. 31.31.</note> thoſe new Couenants
<pb facs="tcp:15622:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>in <hi>Ieremy,</hi> thoſe new Commandements in <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 13.14. Math. 26.28. Heb. 10.20. Ezech. 18.31.</note> thoſe new Teſtaments in <hi>Matthew;</hi> thoſe new liuing wayes in <hi>Paule;</hi> thoſe new beleeuing hearts in <hi>Ezechiell,</hi> to make them new Creatures, yea new men, to giue them new names, and to make them capable of a new Heauen, and new Earth.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this is, to exhort euery one in this great and Honourable aſſembly, to leaue off the iniquitie of his heart, and to bee changed by the renuing of his minde, that hee may prooue the good will of GOD, acceptable and perfect; Caſt of the Morian skinne, expunge the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pards ſpottes, flye out of <hi>Babell,</hi> haſte out of <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> Goe not back, looke not back, but for euer Conſecrate thy ſelfe, thy ſoule, thy body, to thy GOD, and <hi>let his word dwell plenteouſly in thee in all wiſdome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You my Brethren, now admitted into the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred function of the Cleargie, remember this, Preach this, practiſe this, <hi>Let not a white hayre of lightneſſe bee found vppon your blacke garments, nor a blacke ſpotte of filthineſſe polute your white ſurpliſses,</hi> take heed of the <hi>moate of Schiſme,</hi> and <hi>beame of ſuperſtition;</hi> let your Garments haue the high Prieſts <hi>Pomegranates,</hi> as well as <hi>Bells,</hi> your Lampes be as well inwardly <hi>burning,</hi> as outwardly <hi>lighting,</hi> and neuer be weary of the worke of the Lord,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> in as much as your labor is not in vain in the
<pb facs="tcp:15622:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord, and he that promiſeth wil performe, though in this laſt and worſt age, he that hath ſtepped but two ſteppes from the dunghill, ſuch whoſe fathers <hi>Iob</hi> would not haue placed with the Dogges of his ſheepfold, though theſe crauen gallants bee ready to abaſe and abuſe this ſacted <hi>Calling,</hi> yet remember yee that <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, hath dignified this profeſſion, and at this day there is no <hi>Prince</hi> in the Chriſtian world, but hath in him ſome part of a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> beſides that <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> hath, in waſhing vs all from our ſinnes, made vs <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> to <hi>God</hi> his <hi>Father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 1.5.</note> Thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this dignity, practiſe that duty, and ſo <hi>the Lord be with you, and with your ſpirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All of you my beloued heare the ſumme of all: you that come to be either ſpectators, or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary attendants at this great ſolemnity of the CREATION, powre forth your praiers; Firſt for the moſt gratious PRINCE, who is to bee <hi>Created,</hi> that hee may anſwer all thoſe worthy expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of him, and bee as renowned as <hi>Solomon,</hi> that preaching Prince, or <hi>Conſtantine</hi> that praying Prince, or <hi>Theodoſius</hi> that religious Prince, or our moſt Religious, Gratious, Zealous, and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly-preſerued Soueraigne, who hath ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Peace bleſſed vs, and ſo worthily by his Pen conquered his enemies: And if for <hi>Nebuchadnet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> and <hi>Balſhaſſar</hi> his ſonne, prayers were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee made when they were Heathens and
<pb facs="tcp:15622:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>oppreſſors, much more now are prayers to be powred forth plentifully, for our moſt <hi>ſacred Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,</hi> and his <hi>Princely Sonne,</hi> that their daies may be as the daies of heauen, that in their time the righteous may flouriſh, and there may be aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of peace ſo long as the Sunne and Moone endureth, that they may deliuer the poore when he cryeth, the wearie alſo, and him that hath no hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, they may liue, and vnto them may be giuen of the gold of Arabia, their names may endure for euer among the poſterities, which ſhall be bleſſed by them, and all the people ſhall praiſe them.</p>
            <p>And for our ſelues let vs celebrate this happie <hi>Creation</hi> with a <hi>new Creation;</hi> the Sunne renueth, the Moone renueth, the yeare renueth, the ſpring renueth, the morning renueth, this very houre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth. Shall we continue old, dull, dead? The <hi>Hart</hi> renueth ſtrength, the <hi>Swallow</hi> ſight, the <hi>Eagle</hi> youth, yea the very <hi>Viper</hi> renueth and caſteth his ſlough, ſhall we be worſe then the <hi>Viper?</hi> Doe wee looke for new wonders, and make our ſelues new prodigies? Is the miſery of the world ſuch, that men will not be renued or anew created? vnleſſe the courſe of the world be altered, or the pillars of the earth mooued, or the chambers of the deepe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered? muſt the Sea diuide as to <hi>Moſes?</hi> or Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan flie backe as to <hi>Iſrael?</hi> or the Sunne ſtand ſtill as to <hi>Ioſuah?</hi> or goe backe as to <hi>Hezechiah?</hi> or a voice be heard from heauen as to <hi>Paule?</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> doth vſe ordinarie meanes, the preaching of the
<pb facs="tcp:15622:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Goſpell, but extraordinarily: if it pierce thy ſoule, thou art new <hi>Created, God</hi> rather deſireth bleeding hearts, then itching eares. If thou finde this word to be powerfull in thee, and to moue in thy ſoule as <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> leaped in his mothers wombe, Take vp thy bed, and riſe, and walke, thou art healed, thou art this day <hi>Created,</hi> make much of that ſweet Nightingale in the cage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> goeth home with thee, and will enter, dwell with thee, and thou ſhalt ſerue the Lord in righteouſneſſe and holineſſe all the dayes of thy life: practiſe this, and pray for this, and cry euery man vnto God, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, who onely doth marueilous things, and bleſſed be the name of his Maieſtie for euer and euer: And let all the people ſay,</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15622:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
